The Norman R. Peters Collection, 1965-1981
Indiana University Digital Library Program
The Norman R. Peters Collection
1965-1981
Liberian Collections Indiana University 504 North Fess Avenue Bloomington, IN 47408 Phone: (812) 856-0782 Email: liberia@indiana.edu http://www.onliberia.org
Norman R. Peters
LCP2011/03
1 cubic foot; 1 records carton
Norman R. Peters was a member of the United States Peace Corps who spent over four years in Liberia. The collection contains handwritten and typed stories regarding the local Gborbo Krahn people as well as news related material on the 1980 coup.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research
Biographical Note
After extensive training for the Peace Corps in San Francisco and St. Thomas, Group Seven left for Liberia. Arriving at Monrovia in early 1966, Peters continued with several more days of orientation until he was assigned a post. His assignment to the Government School at Zai Town, now named Zaiyee, in the Gborbo Chiefdom northwest of Zwedru.
After several months, Peters realized there was a major culture change going on and decided to document it. He documented the surrounding Krahn culture and history. After two years in Grand Gedeh County he was transferred to Monrovia and taught for an additional two years at the G.W. Gibson School in Bishop Brook. He left the Peace Corps service in January 1970, but returned back to Liberia numerous times between then and 1985.
Peters has also donated his Krahn art collection to the Indiana University Art Museum.
Arrangement
The Norman R. Peters Collection has been divided into two series, Histories and Subject Files. Folders have been divided by series and then chronologically with undated files first. The item level order has been maintained to originality
Scope and Content
The Norman R. Peters Collection consists of 1 linear foot of documents spanning from 1965-1981. The collection has been divided into two series: Histories, and Subject Files.
Histories consists of handwritten and typed documents detailing history and folktales as seen through the local's eyes
Subject Files consists of an inventory and description of Peters' donation to the Indiana University Art Museum. There is also a collection of business cards from members and leaders of the People's Redemption Council.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index this collection.
Names
Peters, Norman R.
Peace Corps (U.S.)
Liberia. People's Redemption Council
Places
Gborbo Chiefdom
Grand Jide County (Liberia)
Liberia
Monrovia (Liberia)
Zai Town
Zaiyee
Topics
Krahn (African people)
Administrative Information
Copyright Transferred
Copyright interests for this collection have not been transferred to the Trustees of Indiana University. Users seeking permissions prior to citing, quoting, or publishing from this correspondence in a way that can identify the writer may consult the Liberian Collections Project at Indiana University for guidance in contacting the copyright owners.
- Histories (Box 1)
  - Gborbo Folktales and the Government School, undated
  - Krahn and Gborbo History File, undated
  - West African History Book, undated
  - The History of the Gborbo Cheifdom and the Gborbo People, 1967
  - The History of the Gborbo People and the Quarters of the Town of Tuzon/Tuzohn, 1968
- Subject Files
  - Various Documents about Liberia and other Ethnic Groups, 1965-1969
  - News Articles about the 1980 and Aftermath, 1980
  - Artifact Sheets of the Collection at the Indiana University Art Museum, 1966-1968
  - Business Cards from Members of the People's Redemption Council Government, 1980-1981